Good morning. Or today's דף *Daf* קכ"ח *Kuf-Kaf-Ches* 128,
we start at the bottom of קכ"ז עמוד ב' *Kuf-Kaf-Zayin Amud Bais*,
שתי נקודות *Shetei Nekudot*, about ten lines from the bottom, נשחטה הבהמה
*Nishchata Habehemah*. And the issue here at stake is that the משנה
mishna. *Mishna* spoke again about the dangling limb. If you remember, that's
something that we've been going back to a little bit, and the
issue around that was that you have a dangling piece of meat
or a dangling limb. If while the animal is alive, it's considered
like food, even though it's not and it's not part of the
animal, but it's not an אבר מן החי ever min hachai, *Ever
min Hachai*. If the animal is שחט shecht *Shechted*, thank you, then
it is not, you can't eat it. We learned that much earlier
in the מסכת *Maseches* from בשר בשדה טריפה basar basadeh treifa *Basar
Basadeh Treifah*.
But nevertheless, it is not a נבילה neveila *Neveilah*. It's considered food.
It's susceptible to becoming טמא tamei? *Tamei*. And the question is: does
the act of שחיטה shechita *Shechita* make it susceptible? Is that הכשר
hechsher, *Hechsher*? Or does it have to come in contact with liquid?
Remember that the act of שחיטה shechita, *Shechita*, both the act of
שחיטה shechita *Shechita* and the blood of שחיטה shechita *Shechita*, makes the
meat of a normal animal susceptible for טומאה tumah. *Tumah*, הכשר hechsher,
*Hechsher*. The question is: does that apply to this dangling piece of
meat or dangling limb? So let's take a look. That was a
debate in the משנה mishna, *Mishna*. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbi Meir*
says it does, and רבי Rabbi שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* says it does
not. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, נשחטה הבהמה במאי קמיפלגי *Nishchata
Habehemah be-mai kamifligi*? What are they debating? אמר רבה *Amar Rabba*, הבהמה
נעשית יד yad לאבר קמיפלגי *Habehemah na'asis yad le-ever kamifligi*. So remember
from the beginning of this פרק *Perek*, we've been dealing with the
issue of יד yad *Yad*, a handle.
And if something has a handle like a bone attached to a
piece of meat, that's a way of communicating טומאה tumah, *Tumah* back
and forth from the meat. If, however, the question and also there
was an issue about whether there is הכשר hechsher, *Hechsher* for the
יד yad, *Yad*. If liquid fell on the bone, was it like
liquid fell on the meat so the meat is susceptible? We are
assuming now there is a concept of הכשר hechsher? *Hechsher* for יד
yad, *Yad*, but the question here is: can something that is a
hundred times as big and more important be a יד yad *Yad*,
handle, for something that is tiny and insignificant? So you've got this
huge cow, this little dangling piece of meat, and the blood of
the שחיטה shechita *Shechita* touches the cow. So is the cow a
handle for the tiny little piece of meat, so it's like the
blood touched the meat and makes the meat susceptible? So we're assuming
there's a concept of יד yad, *Yad* for הכשר hechsher *Hechsher* for
becoming susceptible with liquid, but the conceptual question is: can something that
is clearly much more significant and larger be considered secondary and a
handle to the dangling piece of meat? Charlie had his hand up
first. Charlie?
Charlie asks: Did we deal with this before with a base of
a bone and a זית *zayis* of marrow and the big thigh
with the big bone and the...
Yes, but there, that's a good point, but it wasn't the same.
I would say proportionally it wasn't the same, and also very much
functionally you could say that the bone is secondary to the marrow.
You know, there's also the question of conceptually: can the... The purpose
of the bone is to protect the marrow, or the bone has
its own purpose of structure and so on. But it's very, very
different when here conceptually there's no question that the dangling meat is
secondary to the cow. So, but yeah, that's a good point. Yes,
Bob?
Does the blood... The blood of the שחיטה shechitah.
*Shechita* is considered הכשר hechsher *Hechsher* on the animal.
Was it also on the dangling limb? I mean, was it just
conceptually, metaphorically on the dangling limb
or actually on the...
That's the question.
No, it was not on the dangling. That's the point. Is the
blood on the animal like it came in contact with the limb
because is the animal a יד yad, *Yad* to the limb? So
that's how רבה *Rabba* understands the debate. מר סבר mar savar, *Mar
savar*, אין בהמה behemah, נעשית יד yad. לאבר *Ein behemah na'asis yad
le-ever*. It does not, and therefore it is not הוכשר huchshar. *Huchshar*.
ומר סבר Umar savar, *U-mar savar*, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's *Rebbi
Meir* holds, בהמה behemah נעשית יד yad לאבר *Behemah na'asis yad le-ever*.
It is a handle even to this tiny limb and therefore it
is הוכשר huchshar. *Huchshar*. That's one explanation. אביי Abaye אמר *Abaye amar*,
באוחז בקטן ואין גדול עולה עמו קמיפלגי *Be-ocheiz be-katan ve-ein gadol oleh
imo kamifligi*. Here's an interesting question of how do you define integrity
of an object or unity of an object. You have this big
thing. Now, if you were to lift up the cow, the little
dangling limb would come with it. But if you were to lift
up the limb, the cow wouldn't come with it, it would break
off. So is that considered one unity or not? When you focus
on one part, the other part שלעפּס *Shleps* along, but when you
focus on the small part, the big part won't שלעפּס *Shleps* along.
So it's, you know, it's only sort of connected if you work
in one direction conceptually. Is that considered one unit or not? If
it's one unit, then you don't need the concept of יד yad
*Yad*. Then the liquid that's on the cow goes on the whole
cow. So the question is: is this limb one unit with the
cow or not? So if you lift up the small one but
the big one doesn't come with it, מר סבר *Mar savar*, one
holds, אוחז בקטן ואין גדול עולה עמו הרי הוא כמוהו *Ocheiz be-katan
ve-ein gadol oleh imo harei hu kamosho*. Even if when you hold
the small one if the big one doesn't שלעפּס *Shleps* along, nevertheless
it can still be one unit. ומר סבר *U-mar savar*, and the
other holds, אינו כמוהו *Eino kamosho*. No, it's not one unit and
therefore forget the idea of
יד yad *Yad*. The question is whether it's all one unit or
not. יד yad *Yad* is not the issue. ואף רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan סבר באוחז בקטן ואין גדול עולה עמו קמיפלגי *Ve-af Rebbi Yochanan
savar be-ocheiz be-katan ve-ein gadol oleh imo kamifligi*. That's even רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan's* take on this debate. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
רמי דרבי מאיר אדרבי מאיר *Rebbi Yochanan rami de-Rebbi Meir a-de-Rebbi Meir*.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan* shows a contradiction of two רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir *Rebbi Meir's*. מי אמר רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Mi
amar Rebbi Meir*? How... remember, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's *Rebbi Meir* in
our משנה mishna *Mishna* says the blood of the שחיטה shechitah *Shechita*
works for the limb. So that would mean, if you frame the
debate like we just did, that even if you pull the small
one, the big one doesn't come with it, it's still one unit.
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rebbi Yochanan* said, מי אמר רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir אוחז בקטן ואין גדול עולה עמו *Mi amar Rebbi Meir
ocheiz be-katan ve-ein gadol oleh imo*... Did he really say this, that
if you hold the small one and the big one doesn't come
with it, it's still one unit? ורמיהו, I'll ask you on this.
We have the following משנה. mishna אוכל שנפרס ומעורה במקצת, Ochel shenifras
u'me'ura b'miktzat, a similar thing, except here it's about, you know, not
about a big cow, it's about a piece of food. You have
a little piece of bread or whatever, a little bit is like
broken off and it's dangling by a tiny little point of connection,
and it's the same scenario. If you were to take the big
piece of bread, the small one would come with it. If you
were to try to lift it up by the small piece, it
would break off. Okay, and now you have a טבול יום. tvul
yom. A טבול יום tvul yom is somebody that's gone to the
מקוה mikvah that day and he's going to be טהור tahor that
night, and he can still make תרומה, terumah, he can make it
into a שלישי. shlishi. He's a שני, sheni, he can make only
תרומה terumah into a שלישי. shlishi. And this piece of bread is
תרומה. terumah. And he touches one part of it, the dangling part,
or the other part, the non-dangling. Does the other part become טמא?
tamei. Is it one unit or not one unit? So רבי מאיר
אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, top of קח עמוד א, kuf chet amud
aleph, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, אם אוחז בקטן וגדול
עולה עמו הרי הוא כמוהו, im ochez bakatan v'gadol oleh imo harei
hu kimoho, if you were to pick up the small part of
it, the big part would come along, then it's one unit and
if you touch either part of that bread, the whole bread becomes
טמא. tamei. ואם לאו אינו כמוהו, v'im lav eino kimoho, otherwise it's
two separate units.
And you know, that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. Fine, and there
might be another position. But what you have here is that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that it's only one unit if when you
pick the small part, the big part comes along. And in our
משנה, mishna, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the blood makes it הוכשר.
huchshar And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan understood that the reason for רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir blood of the animal made the limb considered susceptible
is because even though you can't pull the big one through the
small one, it's one unit. So what does he say? When you
have the scenario that the big won't come along with the small,
by the animal he considers it one unit and by the piece
of bread he considers it two units. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
contradicts himself. Now, as the גמרא Gemara is implicitly saying, that's only
if you frame the issue in our משנה mishna. that way. You
could frame the debate in our משנה mishna another way that it's
not a problem. But רבי Rabbi יוחנן understood that that was what
was going on in the משנה, mishna. so he had a contradiction.
So ואמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan, so what does רבי Rabbi
יוחנן say? מוחלפת השיטה. muchlefet hashita. It's reversed. You're right. Meaning that's
sort of like not an answer. That's framing the statement, the question.
But he's got a problem. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's reverses himself in
this case about the תרומה terumah bread than he does from our
משנה. mishna Now interestingly, תוספות Tosafot says that the actual גרסא girsa
of that משנה mishna that we have actually has רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir, holding the reverse position. So it's actually not a problem in
the text that we have of that משנה. mishna Actually רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir's is consistent. But as the text that רבי Rabbi יוחנן
had, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was saying the reverse of what he
said in our משנה mishna and he left it as a question.
We've got a problem. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is holding the reverse
position. In our משנה mishna. he says it's one unit in this
scenario. In the case by the bread he says it's two units.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי קושיא, u'mai kushya, why was that
a problem for him? דילמא שאני ליה לרבי מאיר בין טבול יום
לשאר טומאות. dilma shani lei l'Rabbi Meir bein tvul yom l'sha'ar tumot.
Maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir makes a distinction between a טבול יום,
tvul yom, somebody who's been to the מקוה mikvah that day, and
other טומאות. tumot. A טבול יום tvul yom is a very weak,
low-level טומאה. tumah So there רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's prepared to say
it's two units and the other part of the bread won't be
טמא. tamei In our משנה Mishnah where you're dealing about perhaps a
very high level of טומאה, tumah, דאורייתא d'oraita טומאה tumah, at least
potentially, that's coming in contact with the meat, then we would be
strict and we would consider it to be one unit. So maybe
that's the difference.
So he says, תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, no
you can't say that because we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, רבי אומר אחד טבול יום ואחד שאר טומאות. Rabbi omer
echad tvul yom v'echad sha'ar tumot. That the position about the piece
of bread, one unit or two units, would be no distinction whether
it was the טבול יום tvul yom טומאה, tumah the weak טומאה,
tumah. or a very strict טומאה tumah or a very strict טומאה.
tumah So you can't say, oh there we're being more lenient and
considering it two pieces, it's only טבול יום, tvul yom, because רבי
Rabbi's said that, wait a minute, רבי Rabbi said it's all the
same. So the גמרא Gemara says, who cares what רבי Rabbi, said?
ודילמא לרבי לא שאני ליה, v'dilma l'Rabbi lo shani lei, I don't
mean that in general, I mean for רבי Rabbi, יוחנן. ודילמא לרבי
לא שאני ליה, v'dilma l'Rabbi lo shani lei,
maybe רבי Rabbi thinks that it doesn't make a distinction. ולרבי מאיר
שאני ליה, u'l'Rabbi Meir shani lei, but within רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir. reason he seems to be reversing himself is
maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does make a distinction between whether it's
the weaker טבול יום tvul yom טומאה tumah or other stricter טומאות.
tumot. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רבי יאשיה הכי אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Rabbi Yoshiya hachi amar
Rabbi Yochanan. This is what רבי Rabbi's יוחנן means to say. ולדברי
רבי, u'l'divrei Rabbi, according to רבי's Rebbi claim of this משנה Mishnah.
about the piece of bread, that רבי Rebbi claims it doesn't make
a difference what type of a טומאה tumah you're talking about, so
according to רבי, Rebbi מוחלפת השיטה. muchlefet hashita.
According to רבי, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is reversing himself. So רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir, in one place, in our case, says it's one
unit, here he says it's two units. רבי insists there's no difference
about what type of טומאה tumah, it is. So within רבי's claim,
you can't understand רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position because he's reversing himself
from what he says in our משנה. Mishnah Charlie, you had a
question?
I never learned מסכת טבול יום, Masechet Tvul Yom, but
is, I know טבול יום tvul yom טומאה tumah is weaker, but
is it really just rabbinic?
Ah, so you'll notice, excellent question, that I did not say rabbinic,
I said weaker. רש"י Rashi says... טבול יום Tevil Yom is rabbinic
and therefore we would be more lenient. If you take a look
at the גליון הש"ס, Gilyon HaShas, I don't think I ever said
that. If you take a look at the, but you assumed that,
which is not a bad assumption. If you take a look at
the גליון הש"ס, Gilyon HaShas, that's the lower left-hand column at the
very bottom of the page, lower left-hand left margin, he quotes רש"י,
Rashi, he says שהוא טביל דרבנן shehu tevil d'rabbanan and he says
תמוה לי, tamuah li, I am astounded, הא טבול יום הוא טומאה
דאורייתא בפוסל תרומה בנגיעה, ha tevil yom hu tumah d'oraisa b'posel trumah
b'negi'ah, it's a biblical טומאה, tumah it's weak but it's biblical. עיין
סוטה Ayen Sotah etc. והוה ליה לרש"י לומר דטבול יום קלישא
טומאתו, vahava leih l'Rashi lomar d'tevil yom klisha tumahso, he should have
said it's a weaker טומאה tumah. so maybe we'll be more lenient
because it's weak but it's not to say it's rabbinic and he
leaves it as
צריך עיון גדול, tzarich iyun gadol, which means he...
I know you didn't say it but I was thinking how
can
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir be more lenient if it's biblical? So the
way to say it would be that the, not that we're more
lenient by טבול יום, Tevil Yom, but we're more strict by other
טומאות. tumos. The real הלכה halakha is there are two units and
therefore that will keep it as that for טבול יום Tevil Yom
but even though it's biblical but at a stricter טומאה tumah we'll
be stricter and we'll say it's one unit. That would be the
way to frame it. You're right, we couldn't be lenient if it
were not acceptable within the עיקר הדין. ikkar hadin. Okay, but that
question about whether it's rabbinic or not רש"י Rashi says but the
רבי עקיבא איגר, Rabbi Akiva Eiger, that's the גליון הש"ס Gilyon HaShas
can't understand that. Generally we assume טבול יום Tevil Yom is a
biblical טומאה. tumah, Okay, so that's another way of framing the debate,
not about יד yad but about whether it's a one unit or
not in this scenario where one piece doesn't come along with the
other piece, or the big piece doesn't come along with the small
piece. And now the גמרא Gemara goes along and says like this.
רבא אמר ביש יד לטומאה ואין יד להכשר קמיפלגי. Rava amar b'yesh
yad l'tumah v'ein yad l'hechsher kamifligi. Ah this, remember this was a
debate before whether the concept of יד yad applies not only for
conveying טומאה tumah but for הכשר, hechsher. making liquid and making things
susceptible. Everybody would agree that they're two units. Everybody would agree that
the huge cow can be a יד, yad. a handle for the
dangling piece of meat when it comes to טומאה, tumah but the
question is does that work not only for טומאה tumah, but even
for הכשר, hachsher even for coming in contact with liquid and making
susceptible. So if you touch something טמא tamei. to the cow, it
would convey it to the dangling piece of meat, but if you
touch liquid to the cow, maybe that's not like the piece of
meat came in contact with liquid to be made susceptible. That's the
debate. One minute. מר סבר יש יד לטומאה ואין יד להכשר. mar
savar yesh yad l'tumah v'ein yad l'hechsher. Yes, the concept of יד,
yad a handle, conveys טומאה tumah but it does not convey הכשר,
hechsher? liquid of making things susceptible. ומר סבר יש יד לטומאה ולהכשר.
u'mar savar yesh yad l'tumah u'l'hechsher. Yes, it also conveys the idea
of making something susceptible. This is a very fun גמרא Gemara because
you know you have this debate which is not clear what they're
arguing about and it allows for, you know, not like it's not
one of these like tiny tiny details and technical issues, it allows
for a lot of interesting conceptual framings, right? Does a big thing
act as a handle for a small thing? Does it work not
only in טומאה, tumah. does it work for הכשר? hechsher Whether something
is one unit or two units. It leaves open, you know, it
opens the discussion, the possibilities of a lot of interesting ways of
conceptually framing it. Bobby, you had a question? No? Okay, fine. So
now we go on. רב פפא אמר בהכשר קודם מחשבה קמיפלגי. Rav
Pappa amar b'hechsher kodem machshava kamifligi. We're debating what happens if something
comes in contact with liquid before you plan on eating it. Now,
normally, anything that's normally food, we take it for granted that the
intention is to eat it, so it's a non-issue. Whenever an apple
falls off a tree and comes in contact with liquid, we assume
you're going to want to eat the apple. But this dangling limb,
we've got a little bit of a problem. Why do we have
a problem with this dangling limb? Because if the animal were, first
of all, a Jew can't eat it even after you שחט shechted,
the animal. That we learned out earlier in the משנה Mishna, that
the שחיטה shechitah, makes it not נבילה but still not kosher בשר
בשדה טריפה treifah. and so on. A non-Jew could eat it, that's
certainly true. But not only that, had the animal died
without being
שחט, shecht it would have been אסור assur even to a non-Jew,
it would have been considered in the death of the animal אבר
מן החי, ever min hachai. which is אסור assur even to a
non-Jew. So this limb here, while it's dangling from the animal, you
can't pull it off and give it to a non-Jew, אבר מן
החי. ever min hachai, If it were to die naturally, אבר מן
החי, ever min hachai. אסור assur to a non-Jew. The only scenario
that anybody could eat it is if you שחט shechted it and
then give it to a non-Jew. So it's not the type of
thing that is most likely going to be eaten. So that type
of a thing will only be considered food if you're planning on
eating it because it won't naturally be eaten or planning on giving
it to a non-Jew. So what happens if it came in contact
with liquid? The idea of הכשר hechsher is to make it considered
to be like a full status as food. What if that preceded
your intention to actually eat it or give it to a non-Jew?
Will the הכשר hechsher. be legitimate or does it first have to
be defined by you either subjectively or objectively as food and then
come in contact with liquid? So that's what we're saying the scenario
is. Now the problem with saying that scenario is that that's not
spelled out in the משנה. Mishna The משנה Mishna doesn't spell out
when you planned on eating it. We're assuming that that's the scenario
that likely you'll only plan on eating it later and therefore, even
though you שחט shecht it, you're going to eat the cow but
your intention to eat this dangling limb or feed it to a
non-Jew only comes later, so it comes after the blood of the
שחיטה, shechitah after the הכשר. hechsher, And that's... oops, that should be
fine. Okay, so it says, okay, so where are we? רב פפא
אמר בהכשר קודם מחשבה קא מיפלגי. Rav Papa amar behachsher kodem machshava
kamifligi. דתנן, Ditnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah? it actually should
be דתניא. Ditanya. אמר רב יהודה כך היה רבי עקיבא שונה. Amar
Rav Yehuda kach haya Rabbi Akiva shone.
This is what Rabbi Akiva used to teach. חלב שחוטה בכפרים צריך
מחשבה ואין צריך הכשר שכבר הוכשר בשחיטה. Chelev shechuta bakfarim tzarich machshava
ve'ein tzarich hachsher shekvar huchshar bishchita. Now you שחט shecht an animal
and it has חלב. chelev. חלב chelev is forbidden fat. Okay, but
maybe a non-Jew might want it. Now apparently this was in more
demand in the cities than the חלב, chelev, the forbidden fat, than
it was in the villages. רש״י Rashi gives two explanations why. Number
one is there's less meat per capita in the cities than in
the villages. The villages are where they're raising the cows. Okay, the
city has a much greater population. So in the cities there's much
less meat per capita, so חלב, chelev, which is not the real
meat, is in more demand. The other explanation is somewhat of the
opposite. חלב chelev is a delicacy and
in the cities they can afford it, in the villages they can't.
But what do you, which one would you say?
I was going to say thirst, which means in the city people
are more sophisticated, so it becomes...
They like these more unusual tastes. Right, right. Okay. Whatever it is,
this is something that in the villages would not be normally eaten.
So it's sort of like the dangling limb. You can't take it
for granted that it's going to be eaten. Okay, it certainly wouldn't
be eaten normally by Jews because it's אסור. assur. The most it
would be is eaten by non-Jews. Okay, or a Jew who's violating.
So anyway, you שחט shechted the animal and then what would happen
if the חלב chelev came in contact with liquid before there was
an intention to eat it? In a scenario like the villages where
it can't be taken for granted that it will be eaten. So
let's take a look. כך Kach
Rabbi Yehuda said, כך היה רבי עקיבא שונה. kach haya Rabbi Akiva
shone. This is what Rabbi Akiva used to teach. חלב שחוטה בכפרים,
Chelev shechuta bakfarim, חלב chelev of a שחט shechted, animal
in the villages, צריך מחשבה ואין צריך הכשר שכבר הוכשר בשחיטה. tzarich
machshava ve'ein tzarich hachsher shekvar huchshar bishchita.
So the שחיטה shechitah makes it considered susceptible. The blood of the
שחיטה shechitah. applies to the whole animal including the חלב. chelev. This
is not dangling. And then the only thing left is to intend
to eat it. As soon as you have the intention to eat
it, you don't need a הכשר hechsher. to follow. So basically the
defining it as food can come after it came in contact with
the liquid. אמרתי לפניו, Amarti lefanav,
so says Rabbi Yehuda, I said to him, to Rabbi Akiva, למדתנו
רבנו, limadtanu rabbeinu, our master you have taught us, עולשין שלקטן והדיחן
לבהמה, ulshin sheliktan vehidichan lebehema,
if you plucked עולשין ulshin which was some type of a grass
or some type of an herb which was not normally necessarily eaten
by humans, maybe it was more normally animal food. And animal food
is not considered אוכל, ochel, food, to become טמא. tamei So originally
you picked them and you washed them, came in contact with liquid,
לבהמה, lebehema, originally you intended to feed it to animals. So right
now it's not yet halachically food to become טמא tamei. even though
it came in contact with liquid. ונמלך עליהם לאדם, Venimlach aleihem leadam,
then you said, oh you know what, we're going to use this
even on our table, and you plan to make it human food.
So here the definition of food came after the coming in contact
with the liquid, right? It was rinsed when it was animal food
and only afterward was defined as human food. So you have taught
us in that case, שצריך הכשר שני, shetzarich hachsher sheini, it needs
to come in contact with liquid again. That first it has to
be defined as food and then it has to come in contact
with liquid. So this example of חלב chelev should be the exact
same. Something that is not objectively food until you subjectively define it.
First it needs its subjective definition, then it needs to be in
contact with liquid. Chicory
apparently.
Okay, or endive. Yeah, because we use chicory now, but not ordinarily.
We use coffee substitutes or...
Oh, interesting. Okay, and it tends to be pretty bitter, right? Chicory,
yeah, very interesting. Okay. וחזר רבי עקיבא להיות שונה כרבי יהודה Vechazar
Rabbi Akiva lihyot shone k'Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Akiva reversed himself for
his תלמיד. talmid. He says, you know what, you're right. I'm not
being consistent. We should say that you need that order, first intending
to make it food and then coming in contact with liquid. So
that would seem to seal off the possibility of reading that in
the משנה Mishnah because now everybody is holding that you need that
order. But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara is keeping the original position alive.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מר סבר לה כמעיקרא, mar savar lah
k'meikara, one holds like the pre-reversal position. Notice by the way, Rabbi
Meir and Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishna. are both students of
Rabbi Akiva. Okay, so one holds of the pre-reversal position that the
order does not matter and that's Rabbi Meir. So yes, the blood
of the שחיטה shechitah and then you plan to eat it, that's
still okay and it's still הוכשר. ומר סבר לה כחזרה Umar savar
lah k'chazara and Rabbi Shimon holds post-reversal and therefore it is not
הוכשר because the definition of food only came after the contact with
liquid. Yes, Charlie.
If you're basing your opinion on your teacher and your teacher reversed
himself...
Yes, but maybe not. They also had their own opinions. Okay, so
maybe Rabbi Meir, either you could say it two ways, either Rabbi
Meir wasn't around to hear the reversal, or you could say it
that Rabbi Meir actually, you know, the only problem with Rabbi Akiva
was not that it was not a logically acceptable position, just that
he was inconsistent. So Rabbi Meir might say, I actually think that
he should have reversed himself the opposite way. I actually think his
first position made more sense, right? So yes, he's disagreeing with Rabbi
Akiva, but there's nothing problematic with the position itself.
Okay. Interesting confluence of tradition versus logic. Uh-huh.
Yeah, you mean
if Rabbi Akiva had learned something from his
teacher. Yes, he'd absolutely wouldn't go back on it, right? Because his
students would be bound in that sense to that tradition. So we're
clearly talking about some logical derivation. Right, but then why do you
have to agree with your teacher in the first place?
Well, that's what I'm saying about רבי מאיר. רבי מאיר doesn't have
to agree with his teacher, which is how רבי מאיר could hold
the pre-reversal position. No, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was saying to him,
you're not, you רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva are not being consistent.
No, but what I'm saying is רבי מאיר, like what's to stop
רבי מאיר from disagreeing in the first place? What's his reversal position
also?
That is true. I mean, we wouldn't have had a problem with
that, it's just that very conveniently we're being presented with both options
in רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But you're right, what I said to
Charlie is not that רבי מאיר has to say רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva held it. He could just be saying I prefer the pre-reversal
position and I won't be inconsistent. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, רב אשי בריה דרב איקא אמר, Rav Ashi brei de-Rav Ika
amar,
isn't this fun how many different possibilities we have in this משנה?
Mishna, So here's yet another one. ונתענח דם בין סימן לסימן קמיפלגי.
Venitane'ach dam bein siman lesiman kemiflagei. Okay, this is a real אוקימתא,
ukimta, it's not פשט pshat in the משנה at all, but it
allows us to bring in another fun conceptual question we had before.
So what happened is the blood, Bobby was saying, it was not
just on the cow, it actually splattered on the dangling limb. But
then what happened, you wiped it off, and you wiped it off,
you shechted the trachea, some blood splattered on the dangling limb, I
don't know, somehow you were super fast, you wiped it, or maybe
it was
raining, or whatever, anyway, somehow you wiped it off, and then you
finished the שחיטה. shechitah So is the status of the blood that
came out before the שחיטה shechitah. was finished considered blood to create
הכשר? hechsher The only blood that's מכשיר machshir is blood of שחיטה,
shechitah not normally blood of wounds is not מכשיר. machshir. So the
blood that came out before the שחיטה shechitah was finished, is that
blood of שחיטה shechitah or is that blood of wounds? It came
out between the trachea and the esophagus. Now for the rest of
the cow, of course the rest of the cow is going to
get the blood at the end as well when both things are
shechted, and that's blood of שחיטה. shechitah? But this limb only by
chance got the splatter, so it got a splatter earlier in the
process and then was wiped off. It's a real אוקימתא, ukimta, but
it allows us to put in another point.
I always considered שחיטה shechitah like one act.
Ah, so that's exactly going to be the question. Do we consider
it one continuous act or only an act at the end? That
allows us to bring in that old debate. Let me just read
in the text. דאתמר, De-itmar, מר סבר, ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף,
yeshno lishchitah mitichilah ve'ad sof, שחיטה shechitah, is a continuous process from
beginning to end, והאי דמא דשחיטה הוא, vehai dama dishchitah hu, even
the blood that comes out in the middle is blood of שחיטה.
shechitah ומר סבר, אינה לשחיטה אלא בסוף, eino lishchitah ela besof, no,
it only is defined as שחיטה shechitah, at the end, והאי דמא
דמכה הוא, vehai dama demaka hu, it is blood of a wound
not blood of שחיטה shechitah, now. The interesting point is, and this
is always conceptually difficult, what do you mean אינה לשחיטה אלא בסוף?
eino lishchitah ela besof? If you really said it was only the
last thing, the last bit of the act of cutting, then by
the time you shechted it, it would be a טריפה. treifah. So
what does that really mean, אינה לשחיטה אלא בסוף? eino lishchitah ela
besof? So the real point is like this, and this is clear
because it speaks about wiping off the blood. Why did it have
to say wipe off the blood? Why doesn't it just say that
if שחיטה shechitah, is only at the end, then even if you
didn't wipe off the blood, the blood that splattered at the beginning
is not blood of שחיטה? shechitah, Who cares whether you wiped it
off or not? So the point seems to be like this. If
you say there's no שחיטה shechitah, until the end, that means that
only when you finish, only at that stage do you then say
retroactively that the whole process was a process of שחיטה, shechitah but
not proactively. While you're doing the cutting, right now am I doing
an act of שחיטה shechitah as I'm cutting, or right now I
don't know what I'm
doing, I'm injuring, I'm stabbing an animal? When it finishes and it
turns out that it was שחיטה, shechitah now I can retroactively say,
looking back I can say I did an act of שחיטה, shechitah
but not as I'm doing it yet, not until I'm done. So
that seems to be the way of framing the debate. And therefore,
if the blood remained even after I finished the שחיטה, shechitah then
I would retroactively say, oh, I was always doing an act of
שחיטה, shechitah that blood is blood of שחיטה, shechitah, and everybody would
agree it would be מכשיר. machshir. But if I cleaned the blood
off, then if I consider שחיטה shechitah, from the time I'm beginning,
then when it hit, it was blood of שחיטה shechitah and it
was מכשיר. machshir. But if it's only שחיטה shechitah? when I finish
and I look retroactively, at that stage that I'm looking retroactively, the
blood is already cleaned off and can no longer be מכשיר machshir
the meat. So that seems to be, this is actually very important
in helping us understand this debate of whether שחיטה shechitah is from
the beginning or the end, because it's impossible to say it's only
at the end, because then you're shechting an animal that's a טריפה.
So what it really means is, yes, do I define it שחיטה
Shechita as from the very outset, or do I only define it
שחיטה Shechita when I finish retroactively? That's the question, and therefore if
the blood is no longer there, so if I was looking forward
at it as שחיטה, Shechita it was מכשיר. machshir. If I only
look at it backwards as שחיטה, shechita then it's no longer there
and it can no longer be מכשיר. machshir. Yes, Bracha?
But isn't preparation for שחיטה shechita like we learned in ninth has
to be checked? Right, so if someone is standing there and checking
the knife, and
we still don't say he's killing the animal for שחיטה?
shechita No, we do say he's doing it לשם שחיטה, leshem shechitah,
but we won't formally define the act as an act of שחיטה
shechita until it finishes. Maybe it'll get ruined, and maybe if it
gets ruined then it was just, you know, it was a... act
of stabbing and killing an animal. So I'm only prepared to call
it- I know what you're trying to do. You're trying to do
שחיטה shechita but I'm not prepared to call it a שחיטה shechita
until you actually succeed. That's the definition of אין שחיטה אלא בסוף.
Ein Shechita Ela B'sof.
Yes. What if necessarily you see blood spatter? At that point would
that be beginning of the end or would that just be...
That's the question, whether when the blood comes out as you're beginning,
are we already calling it שחיטה shechita or we're not yet prepared
to... Right, or we're not yet prepared to until you finish. Okay,
so that gets us back to that debate from a long time
ago, but actually it's helpful in clarifying that debate.
Now we have yet another one. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar,
בשחיטה מכשרת ולא דם קמיפלגי. b'shechita machshert v'lo dam kamiflagi.
And he only had to say actually about five words for this
because you're supposed to remember and this was a great debate before
in the משנה. There's the question about if you had a שחיטה
shechita that somehow magically no blood came out, would the act of
שחיטה shechita alone be a substitute for הכשר hechsher for liquid? Because
if the whole idea of הכשר hechsher, is it makes something into
food by water coming in contact with it, it's like it more
fully defines it as food. Maybe the act of שחיטה shechita which
makes this animal food doesn't need הכשר. hechsher Okay, so there was
a position that said שחיטה shechita, by itself without blood serves as
הכשר, but it also said that the flip of that, that the
blood of שחיטה shechita does not create הכשר. The only thing that
creates הכשר is the שחיטה shechitah... itself. Now how does that play
out here? Because this dangling piece of meat is not- you're not
allowed to eat it. Okay, that's the הלכה halacha we learned a
long time ago, if it was dangling and you שחט, you can't
eat that piece of meat. So the שחיטה shechitah. did not turn
this dangling piece of meat into food because even with the שחיטה
shechitah. you're not allowed to eat it. So if the way שחיטה
shechitah. makes the meat susceptible is by making it fit to be
eaten, then it doesn't apply to this dangling piece of meat. If
the way שחיטה shechitah makes the food susceptible is through blood of
שחיטה, shechitah. well the blood, since it splattered on the cow, presumably
we'll call it one unit or a יד yad or whatever we'll
call it, and we'll say that it also affects the dangling piece
of meat. So this is the question: why does שחיטה shechitah. make
it susceptible? By turning it into food or because of the blood?
The blood applies to both, but the making it food only applies
to the cow, not to the dangling meat. Okay, so that is
yet another way of framing the debate.
So, where are we? Okay, right. רב אשי, Rav Ashi, we just
did that.
בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, now that we're done with about six different
ways of explaining the debate, now we get into some other interesting
questions about יד, yad. because we already had one fascinating question about
יד, yad? which is: can an entire cow be a handle to
a little dangling limb? So now we're going to get into other
questions of whether things can be- what types of things can and
cannot be considered a יד. yad? So let's take a look. בעי
רבא, Ba'ei Rava, בהמה בחייה מה שתעשה יד לאבר. behema b'chayeha mah
shete'aseh yad l'eiver. You've
got
this dangling limb, right? Remember we said that even while the animal
is alive, the dangling limb is considered food and it can become
טמא. tamei. Okay, but let's say liquid did not fall on the
dangling limb with this live cow, it fell on the cow. Can
a living, breathing cow be a יד yad, for a dangling limb?
Our question was: can a dead cow be a יד yad. because
it's huge and it's more important? Let's say the answer to that
is yes. How about if the cow was alive? Could then it
become a יד yad to bring either הכשר or טומאה tumah, to
the dangling limb? That is the question. Okay, it's not clear. רש"י
Rashi says we're no longer talking about הכשר, we're talking about טומאה.
tumah But either way, that's the question about can the living cow
be a יד yad? for the dangling
limb. בהמה בחייה מה שתעשה יד לאבר? Behema b'chayeha mah shete'aseh yad
l'eiver? תיקו. Teiku. We don't know the answer, that's a really good
question. Now,
תוספות, Tosafot, רש"י Rashi already points out, תוספות Tosafot clarifies that we
already know that you can have a יד yad of something that
itself cannot become טמא. tamei A bone can be a יד yad
to the meat. But that is just it's not טמא tamei. because
it's not food. The types of questions we're going to be asking
are things that might be food but are more categorically excluded. So
for example, a breathing cow is like a whole living thing, you
know, that might be completely categorically excluded and not the same as
just being bones and not edible. There'll be other types of things
like that. Normally you don't need it to be food, but how
about these things? Are these categories so different that it can't- it's
completely removed, let's say, from the world of טומאה, tumah completely excluded,
that it cannot even serve as a יד. yad So let's see
another similar question. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, הרי אמרו, harei amru, there's
a
משנה, קישות שנטעה בעציץ. kishut sheneta'ah b'atzitz. You have this קישות, kishut,
again, I don't know, some vegetable, you will tell me what that
is, somebody? Cucumber. Cucumber, okay. Anyway, it's planted in an עציץ, atzitz,
a flower pot. Now the flower pot does not have a hole
in it, so therefore it's not considered connected to the ground when
it's growing in a flower pot. והגדילה ויצאה חוץ לעציץ. v'higdila v'yatza
chutz l'atzitz. And now it is- cucumbers grow on vines, right? So
apparently the vine is now- reaches over the edges of the flower
pot and some part of the vine or some part of the
cucumber is now suspended over the ground. You have your flower pot
on your- in your backyard. backyard, so the part that's going beyond
the parameters of the flower pot are now suspended over the ground.
Okay, so what's the הלכה halacha of that? טהורה. Tehorah. So says
the part that the part that is over ground is like it's
connected to ground, and something that's מחובר לקרקע mechubar l'karka connected to
ground cannot become טמא. tamei. The part that is growing in the
pot is considered disconnected, it's like it's cut, and can become טמא.
tamei. So if I touch טומאה tumah. to the cucumber over the
ground, it's טהור, tahor, to the cucumber over of the pot, it's
טמא. tamei So now the question is, can the part that's over
the ground that's considered מחובר mechubar be a יד yad? for the
part that's in the pot?
Okay, so it's the same thing, it's both connected to the same
living thing and one could be one part tamei, one part exactly.
And you sort of have that by the dangling limb of the
cow, but here's a little bit more bizarre because here they're very,
it's still very, you know,
it's really one unit, it's totally fully connected. Right, that is the
הלכה. halacha. So that's why he wants to know, אמר רבי שמעון,
Amar Rabbi Shimon, anyway, Rabbi Shimon disagrees with this. וכי מה טיבה
לטהר? V'chi mah tivah l'taher? Anyway, oh, I'm sorry, I jumped Rabbi
Shimon. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says the whole cucumber plant is
טהור. tahor. So that saves us from that bizarre situation. But Rabbi
Shimon rejects that. אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, Rabbi Shimon says,
וכי מה טיבה לטהר? V'chi mah tivah l'taher? How does the part
that's connected to the ground purify the part that's in the pot?
אלא הטמא בטומאתו והטהור בטהרתו. Ella hatamei b'tumato v'hatahor b'taharato. The part
that could become טמא tamei that's in the pot can still become
טמא tamei or remains טמא tamei, if it were טמא, tamei. and
the part that's over the ground is considered connected and טהור tahor
even if it's the same cucumber or the same vine. One minute,
let's just read the question. So בעי אביי, Ba'ei Abaye, so Abaye
asks similar to Rava's question about the living cow, מהו שתעשה יד
לחברתה? Mahu shete'aseh yad l'chavertah? Can the part of the cucumber that's
considered מחובר mechubar connected be a יד to bring טומאה tumah. or
to bring הכשר to the part that's in the pot even though
it's literally the same vine or the same cucumber? תיקו, Teiku, we
don't know. So again, non-foods can be a יד. Now we're asking
different things. Can living, breathing animals be a יד? Can something that's
מחובר לקרקע mechubar l'karka be a יד? Okay, these might be more
categorically excluded than things that are just non-foods. Yes, Charlie.
Isn't it true that biblically an entity is either entire tamei or
entirely tahor? This must be rabbinic tumah.
Well, that's an interesting point. By for humans that is, like you're
probably thinking about the whole concept of טומאת ידים tumas yadayim and
washing hands is only rabbinic because either the whole human is or
the whole human is not. But it's not the same for this.
There's no suggestion here that this is only rabbinic, and I think
it's because that, you know, in theory this is more of an
object than a subject. So a human being is a subject, you
know, it's like, it's not subdividable.
A cucumber you can cut it in half and it's just an
object. So the fact that it happens to be one unit does
not prevent you saying that this half is tamei and that half
is tahor. If you look at it as an object, there's not
a problem sort of seeing a dividing line. What you're thinking about
is about humans. That's certainly true about humans.
You can't keep a part pre-thrown in the border of ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and half yeah, so we're going to have a similar
case to that.
This is sort of a structural... at what point in the debate
do they just finally say teiku?
So often if there's like no
good, well, in this case they're saying teiku pretty quickly. Usually that
is if there's no textual evidence and no good way to make
an analogy and no good logical argument, there's nothing to really say
about it. So okay, that was a great question, we have no
information to bring to bear, so we'll just have to leave it.
So some, you know,
that's a good question, most teikus I think are like that. I
have to think about it, but most teikus
come pretty quickly after the question was framed. I'm trying to think
when you would have a teiku after there's let's say a significant
debate and we'll still end in a teiku. It will happen, but
I think that's rarer. I think this is more the classic way
teiku is introduced. Okay, yeah.
Yeah, I'm still bothered by the saying that
שחיטה...
is
there any other example of something that we say that... like when
you light Shabbos candles, you say a bracha before you light.
Right, I understand,
you say a bracha before you do the שחיטה. I understand, you
do a bracha before you do the שחיטה. Yeah, but it's not
because we're, it's not because, you know, maybe I suggested that, it's
not because we think it's likely you won't succeed.
We're assuming you will succeed and therefore you're right, you're ready, you're
prepared to make a bracha, we'll do all that, but we will
not formally label it as such until it actually is done. Okay,
until it's done and has success, we're not prepared to call it
an act of שחיטה. Yeah, there are cases about שחיטה about ישנה
מתחילה ועד סוף yeshnah m'techilah v'ad sof or not, not just by
שחיטה. I'm trying to think, ישנה... a couple of questions about process
questions.
Mordechai was asked
a couple days ago that the end process made the previous
things...
Yeah, yeah, okay, I have to get back to you that there
are definitely a couple of questions where this ישנה מתחילה ועד סוף
or not, the classic example is שחיטה. but there are a couple
of other applications about this. So, okay. And again, it's not that
we don't think you'll succeed, it's when are we prepared to give
it the label. All right, let's go back—let's go on. Okay, so
אביי Abaye wants to know, רבא Rava wants to know about the
living cow as a יד, אביי wants to know about מחובר mechubar
as a יד. Let's have another case. Now we're having fun. אמר
רבי ירמיה: Amar Rabbi Yirmiya: הרי אמרו המשתחוה לחצי דלעת אסרה. Harei
amru, hamishtachaveh lachatzi dala'at asrah. Here you have another case of half,
Charlie, and somewhat similar to your case James. Somebody who bows down
and worships half of a gourd. So that half of a gourd
is עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, the other half is not עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. Now,
what's the story of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Well, number one is
עבודה זרה avodah zarah actually has rabbinic טומאה. tumah But we're going
to bracket that, there's two ways of explaining this. I'm going to
explain it one of the ways of רש״י Rashi for simplicity. We're
going to bracket the rabbinic טומאה. tumah עבודה זרה avodah zarah is
also forbidden in benefit. Now, if something might be edible but because
you can't get benefit from it is not considered food. And therefore
if it's not food, it would not become טמא. tamei. So the
half of the gourd that's עבודה זרה avodah zarah cannot be eaten,
it's forbidden in benefit, you can't even feed it to a non-Jew
because you'd be getting benefit that way. It's not food, it cannot
become טמא. tamei, Can it communicate as a יד for the other
half that is food? Now again, this is different from a bone,
a bone is just not edible. This is edible but it's categorically
excluded because it's forbidden in benefit. Does that take it out of
the category so it can't even serve as a יד? So let's
take a look. So בעי רבי ירמיה, ba'ei Rabbi Yirmiya, so therefore
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya asked based on this case, מה שתעשה יד
לחברתה? mah shetei'aseh yad lachaverta? Can that half that's עבודה זרה avodah
zarah be an idol, be a יד to the other half of
the gourd? And the גמרא Gemara says: תיקו. Teiku. We don't know,
the position stands. אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: הרי אמרו. Harei
amru. Okay, let's see how many more we can get. ייחור של
תאנה שנפשח ומעורה בקליפתה. Yichur shel te'enah shenifshach ume'ur b'klipata.
You have a branch of a fig tree that has been pulled
out, like broken off, but you know, it's not fully broken. It
still has the bark is still keeping it somewhat hanging and dangling
and connected. Sort of like our dangling limb, okay? What is the
status of that dangling limb of the tree? So רבי יהודה מטהר,
Rabbi Yehuda metaher, it's like it's broken from the tree—it's still, excuse
me, connected to the tree says רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. And therefore
it's connected to the ground and it cannot become טמא, tamei, the
fruit that's on it. וחכמים אומרים, V'chachamim omrim, and the Rabbis say
it depends. אם יכול לחיות טהור ואם לאו טמא. Im yachol lichyot,
tahor v'im lav, tamei. If it can, you know, if that limb
can survive, then it's considered connected to the tree and it can't
become טמא, tamei. it's טהור. tahor. If it cannot survive, so it's
not connected to the tree, even though physically it still is, it's
not considered, it's not in a living way connected and therefore the
fruit on it is like it's picked and the fruit on it
can become
טמא. tamei So בעי רב פפא, ba'ei Rav Papa, מה שתעשה יד
לחברו? mah shetei'aseh yad lachavero? תיקו. Teiku. Let's say the tree—maybe this
is even the better case James of you—the tree is like the
cucumber case but it's maybe even a little bit more physically, you
know, this scenario. The whole big tree is מחובר לקרקע. mechubar lekarka.
Can it be a יד if something טמא tamei. touches the tree
to this dangling branch that is not halachically considered to be, you
know, that's considered to be not connected? Now physically they're connected but
halachically this branch is not considered growing from the ground anymore and
can become טמא. tamei So if you touch something to the tree,
will it communicate it to the branch? Again, can something connected to
the ground be a יד for something that is not connected to
the ground? So the גמרא Gemara says, any guesses? תיקו. Teiku. אמר
רב זירא: Amar Rabbi Zeira: הרי אמרו. Harei amru. Last case. אבן
שבזווית. Even she'be'zavit. You have a house that is becoming טמא tamei,
from צרעת, tzara'at, right? This whatever spots, leprosy we'll call it. Now
the point is is that you have to, under certain stages you
have to remove the stones, replace them, plaster. When it really is
the worst level of טומאה tumah, you shatter the stones. So you
have this stone that's in a corner. Now it's a corner, it's
adjoining, we have an attached, you know, semi-attached house. So this cornerstone
here is half in my house and half in your house, right?
That's where the wall runs between that
stone. So אבן שבזווית כשחולץ חולץ את כולו. even she'be'zavit, k'she'choletz, choletz
et kulo. When it's at the status of what's called חליצה, chalitzah,
the earlier status of טומאה tumah where it's removed, so you remove
the entire stone. וכשנותץ, uk'she'notetz,
but when it's shattered, which is the worst level of טומאה, tumah
the highest stage, so נותץ את שלו ומניח את של חברו. notetz
et shelo u'mani'ach et shel chavero. You only have to shatter the
half that's in my house, not—you can leave the half that's in
your house. Okay, why we're not going to bother ourselves with, we'll
just acknowledge that. So what you see is is that when it's
at that status, the half that is of shattering it, only the
half that has the leprosy on it is טמא, tamei? the half
that's in your house is טהור, tahor, you don't have to do
anything with it. So let's say something touches the stone in your
house, the half that's טהור. tahor. Will the half of the stone
that's טהור tahor communicate the טומאה tuma from the half that is
טמא? tamei, So בעי רבי זירא, ba'ei Rabbi Zeira,
מה שתעשה יד לחברתה? mah shetei'aseh yad lachaverta? Can the half of
the stone that's טהור tahor be a יד? And again the גמרא
says: תיקו. Teiku. Okay, so that was a lot of fun. Glad
us to explore a lot of different scenarios of things that not
just because they're not food are not טמא, tamei? but have other
categorical ways of being excluded. And can they become a יד *yad*
or not and allow us to explore a lot of different cases.
Now, מיתת הבהמה *meisat habeheimah*. We move on in the משנה *Mishnah*.
The משנה *Mishnah* now says: if the animal was not שחט *shechted*
but died, then the limb is considered this is a principle called
מיתה עושה ניפול *misa oseh nipul*, death causes dropping, falling. Then when
the animal die- when the limb is dangling and the animal's alive,
it's food but it's not yet, it's still part of the animal,
it's not נבילה *neveilah*, it's not אבר מן החי ever min hachai
*eiver min hachai*. The animal is שחט *shechted*, you can't eat it,
but it's also not נבילה *neveilah*. If the animal died naturally, we
say the death of the animal is like the limb fell off
in the- animal as the animal was dying, and the limb becomes
not נבילה *neveilah* because it fell off before the- while before the
animal actually died, and it's אבר מן החי eiver min hachai *eiver
min hachai*. So the משנה *Mishnah* says when the animal dies naturally,
this dangling limb becomes אבר מן החי eiver min hachai, *eiver min
hachai*, not נבילה *neveilah*. So let's take a look at the גמרא
*Gemara*. מאי איכא בין אבר מן החי eiver min hachai לאבר של
נבילה *Mai ika bein eiver min hachai le'eiver shel neveilah*? What difference
does it make if you call it אבר ever. מן החי *eiver
min hachai* or נבילה *neveilah*? Now obviously there's a difference if like
a בן נח *ben Noach* a non-Jew can eat it. But it
means from the world of טומאה tuma *tumah*, who cares? נבילה *neveilah*
causes טומאה tuma *tumah*, אבר ever, מן החי *eiver min hachai* causes
טומאה tuma *tumah*. The משנה *Mishnah* said it's טמא *tamei* like an
אבר ever, מן החי *eiver min hachai*. It's not טמא *tamei* like
a נבילה *neveilah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says what difference does it
matter? Either way causes טומאה tuma *tumah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
איכא בינייהו בשר הפורש ממנו *ika beinyahu basar haporish mimenu*. Let's say
a piece of meat came off of this dangling limb after the
animal died. So, מאבר בהמה behema *me'eiver beheimah*, בשר הפורש ממנו *basar
haporish mimenu*, מאבר בהמה behema *me'eiver beheimah*. דאילו פירש *De'ilu porish* came
off of it of the limb of this animal, this dangling limb.
דאילו בשר הפורש מאבר מן החי לא מטמא metamei, מאבר מן הנבילה
מטמא metamei? *De'ilu basar haporish me'eiver min hachai lo mitamei me'eiver min
haneveilah mitamei*. If the reason this limb is טמא *tamei* is אבר
ever מן החי *eiver min hachai*, אבר ever מן החי *eiver min
hachai* means literally the whole limb, not just some meat from it.
Meat is not what causes טומאה tuma *tumah*, it is the entirety
of the limb. So for example, בשר מן החי basar min hachai.
*basar min hachai*, if I ripped a piece of meat off of
an animal when it was alive, it would not cause טומאה tuma,
*tumah*. It's forbidden to eat, but the only thing that causes טומאה
tuma *tumah* is the whole limb. So if this whole limb is
טמא *tamei* as a limb, then if some meat was removed from
it, it would not cause טומאה tuma. *tumah*. It's only טמא *tamei*
when it's entirely there as a limb. If however it's טמא *tamei*
as נבילה *neveilah*, what causes נבילה *neveilah* טומאה tuma *tumah* is the
meat. So the one difference of whether I call this dangling limb
נבילה *neveilah* or אבר eiver, מן החי *eiver min hachai* is will
the meat alone cause טומאה tuma, *tumah*? For the נבילה *neveilah* the
answer is yes, but for אבר מן החי *eiver min hachai* the
answer is no. It only has to be the entire limb. Okay,
now the גמרא *Gemara* says: אבר מן החי דמטמא מאי קרא *eiver
min hachai demitamei mai kera*? Where is a פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* that
you know that אבר מן החי *eiver min hachai* causes טומאה tuma
*tumah*? So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*:
וכי ימות מן הבהמה vechi yamut min habehemah, *v'chi yamut min habeheimah*,
if one of the animals that you can eat dies, then it's
טמא *tamei* and that's נבילה *neveilah*. So that means, so we're reading
it not that it means not the whole animal dies, but מן
הבהמה min habehemah, *min habeheimah*, some part of the animal dies. What
does it mean a part of the animal? The limb has died,
so the limb was taken off of the animal while the animal
was alive. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says: והא מיבעי ליה לכדרב
יהודה אמר רב *v'ha mibayei lei l'chid'Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*, don't we
need it to tell us the other teaching דאמר רב יהודה אמר
רב *d'Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*? ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא *V'amri lei
bemasnisa tana* and some say we taught in the ברייתא *braisa*: וכי
ימות מן הבהמה מקצת בהמה behema, מטמאה ומקצת בהמה behema אינה מטמאה
*v'chi yamut min habeheimah miktzas beheimah metamei umiktzas beheimah eino metamei*, only
some dead animals cause טומאה tuma *tumah* some do not. ואיזו היא
*V'eizu hi*, what is a dead animal that's like a נבילה *neveilah*
but does not cause טומאה tuma *tumah*? זו טריפה ששחטה *Zu treifah
she'shechatah*, that when you שחט *shecht* an animal that's a טריפה *treifah*,
although you can't eat it because it's a טריפה *treifah*, because it
underwent שחיטה *shechitah*, it does not cause טומאה tuma *tumah*. So we
use the word מן הבהמה *min habeheimah* to tell me not all
dead animals, even those that you can't eat, cause טומאה *tumah*. Only
a נבילה *neveilah*, but one that was שחט *shechted* even if it's-
even if it's a טריפה *treifah* does not cause טומאה *tumah*. So
don't we use the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to tell me that law
and not this law of אבר מן החי *eiver min hachai*? So
the גמרא *Gemara* says: no, אם כן ליכתוב רחמנא מבהמה *im kein
lichtov Rachmana mibeheimah*. It didn't have to use it as a fully
separate word. It could have said 'from a beheimah' with just as
a prefix. מאי מן הבהמה *Mai min habeheimah*? The fact that it
goes out of its way to use this word 'from' as a
separate word, שמע מינה תרתי *shema mina tarti*. It's telling me both
things. Okay, so I learned two things from the פסוק *pasuk* 'from
a beheimah'. Number one is not all בהמות *beheimas*, a טריפה *treifah*
does not cause טומאה *tumah*. And number two is even if something
died that wasn't the whole beheimah, even if only a piece of
the beheimah died, meaning a limb was torn off, that limb causes
טומאה *tumah*.
Okay, not a piece of that limb,
not a piece of it, it has to be the whole limb.
And now we're going to actually ask that, how do we know
it has to be the whole limb? How do we know that
just meat from a beheimah does not? How do we know that
it has to be the whole limb? So that's exactly what we're
going to turn to.
But my question is you said if it's a נבילה *neveilah* then
a piece of the meat would cause- Yes, that's right. But if
it's a piece of the meat of the dangling limb it doesn't?
Correct. Or of the torn limb, correct? Yes, either, correct. Okay, so
now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: אי הכי אפילו בשר נמי
*ei hachi afilu basar nami*. So there you go, that's the question.
If it means part of the animal died, why do you limit
it to a full limb? Maybe even if meat was torn off,
that's like something that died from the animal, maybe just the meat
alone should cause טומאה *tumah*? לא סלקא דעתך *Lo salka daatach*, that
doesn't make sense. דתניא *Detanya* we taught in the ברייתא *braisa*: יכול
יהא בשר הפורש מן החי טמא *yakhol yehei basar haporish min hachai
tamei*, maybe even meat that separated from the living is טמא *tamei*?
that is torn off of a living animal should cause טומאה, תלמוד
לומר Talmud lomar וכי ימות מן הבהמה, if something of the animal
dies, so it has to be like death. מה מיתה שאין לה
חליפין אף כל שאין לו חליפין, mah mitah she-ein lah chalifin af
kol she-ein lo chalifin, דברי רבי יוסי divrei Rabbi Yosei or רבי
יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yosei HaGelili. Death does not sort of replace itself.
If a person dies, I mean even תחיית המתים, techiyat hameitim, but
it won't happen naturally. Okay, so therefore it has to be something
like death. If an animal loses a limb, it won't grow back.
If some flesh falls off, that flesh might heal, the flesh that
left that came off. So therefore it's only something that its removal
is a type of a death, where it's the whole limb that
won't grow back as opposed to just flesh. That's what רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei says. רבי עקיבא אומר בהמה. Rabbi Akiva omer behemah. No,
it has to be like an animal. It's מן הבהמה, it has
to be like an animal. So מה בהמה גידים ועצמות, mah behemah
gidim va'atzamot, the same way an animal has not just meat but
also has, you know, bones and sinews, אף כל גידים ועצמות. af
kol gidim va'atzamot. It's only something that is like an animal in
miniature. So a limb of an animal has all the things, it's
got bones and sinews, that's like a little mini animal. That causes
טומאה but not just meat. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says.
But it doesn't have an organ.
Well, that is true. I mean, you know, we limit obviously it's
not completely and it doesn't move around, it doesn't have locomotion. Right,
it's a very loose analogy. Okay, but it's a way of limiting
the scope of this law. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, Rebbi says בהמה,
behema similar to the בהמה analogy, but he goes one step further.
מה בהמה בשר גידים ועצמות, mah behemah basar gidim va'atzamot, not just
sinews and bones, it's also flesh, sinews, and bones. אף כל בשר
גידים ועצמות, af kol basar gidim va'atzamot, something that has all three
of them. But again, not just meat. Now we're going to clarify
what are the points of debate because they're not just arguing the
פסוק, they're actually arguing the scope of what's considered an אבר מן
החי. So מאי איכא בין רבי לרבי עקיבא? mai ika bein Rebbi
le-Rabbi Akiva? What's the difference between רבי and רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva?
רבי adds, you know, רבי adds meat, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't
mention meat. So איכא בינייהו ארכובה. ika beinaihu arkuva. There is the
ארכובה arkuva which is like the, what do you call, like it's
the lower bone of a, I think the way רש"י Rashi described
it, you know, there's always this thing which is called the ארכובה,
ארכובה הנמכרת עם הראש, arkuva, arkuvah hanimkeret im harosh, which is like
the bottom foot of a cow. And רש"י, Rashi, at least what
רש"י Rashi says is, is that that doesn't actually, that's like a
bone which doesn't have meat. It's hard to imagine an exposed bone
of an animal. I mean, the hoof itself doesn't have meat, but
that's not normally what we would call an אבר.
Less meat on the shin.
On a shin, well that seems to be what רש"י Rashi is
describing, is the shin area. I mean, but it's possible he describes
that all the sort of stuff there is like sinews and not,
but there can't be that there's no meat on it.
Very, very little, it's a very hard area if you. Aha. So
unfortunately I know that. Right.
So that seems to be exactly what רש"י Rashi is describing. But
again, I never fully understood that because it's got, you know, what
do you call, I mean it does have some meat on top
of it.
It has some meat, not just the bone.
Right, and sinews.
So what does
it, what do they say there in Artscroll? The ארכובה. arkuva.
Lower joint. What? Lower joint.
The lower joint of the foot. Yeah, does it say anything in
the notes about how it has no meat? It says
רש"י, Rashi,
lack of flesh, lack of flesh.
Lack of flesh. Okay, well thank you. All right, I don't know.
It says רש"י Rashi and תוספות.
Tosafot. Thank you. Okay, fine. Anyway, all right, so that's that. So
somehow something that's considered effectively to have no flesh, that would be
one difference, that would be the difference between whether you added the
word flesh or not.
Where are we? בין רבי עקיבא לרבי יוסי הגלילי, bein Rabbi Akiva
le-Rabbi Yosei HaGelili, how about between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says
bones and sinews and רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGelili that says
it does not
replace itself? מאי איכא בינייהו? mai ika beinaihu? So here's a very
interesting
one. אמר פפא כוליה וניספתים, amar Pappa kulya venispataim,
kidneys and your lips. So how about if you have a part
of the body that's an organ or an אבר, however you define
אבר, but has no bones? How about all the inner organs? Right?
So what would be the story there? So how about the lips?
So that would be the debate about whether your definition of אבר
requires bones if it naturally does not have bones. Now תוספות Tosafot
claims that if it naturally doesn't have bones, everybody would agree that
it would be an organ. They just use this as an example
and the real question is if something that naturally did have bones
but you had it in its non-bone state. But anyway, the simple
sense here, or no, maybe I'm reframing it, I'm sorry, no, that
was the ריב"א riva about something else. Anyway, the simple sense here
is that they're arguing about something that naturally does not have bones,
basically you could say organs, whether those are considered אבר or not.
Okay, and let's just read basically a repeat of this. תניא נמי
גבי שרצים כהאי גוונא, tanya nami gabei sheratzim keh-hai gavna, we taught
similarly by שרצים, sheratzim, there's also
an אבר מן החי by שרצים, sheratzim, like by rodents and Reptiles,
thank you. יכול בשר הפורש מן השרצים יטמא,
Yachol
basar
haporash min hasheratzim yitamei,
maybe meat that falls off of those שרצים sheratzim will be טמא?
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar במותם, bimotam,
when they die. מה מיתה שאינו עושה חליפין אף כל שאינו עושה
חליפין, Ma mita she'eino osef chalifin af kol she'eino osef chalifin, only
something that's like death, that falls from them that does not get
replaced. דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי, Divrei Rabbi Yose HaGlili,
which would be a full limb. רבי עקיבא אומר שרץ, Rabbi Akiva
omer sheratz, no it has to be like a שרץ. sheratz. מה
שרץ גידים ועצמות אף כל גידים ועצמות. Ma sheratz gidim ve'atzamot af
kol gidim ve'atzamot. It has to have bones and sinews. רבי אומר
שרץ, Rebbe omer sheratz, like a שרץ, sheratz, מה שרץ בשר גידים
ועצמות אף כל בשר גידים ועצמות. ma sheratz basar gidim ve'atzamot af
kol basar gidim ve'atzamot. Same thing except we're debating it not by
cows or sheep but by שרצים. sheratzim. בין רבי לרבי עקיבא איכא
בינייהו ארכובה, Bein Rebbe le-Rabbi Akiva ika beinaihu arkuba, so
whether you add flesh or not is the question about this like
lower limb of the leg. בין רבי עקיבא לרבי יוסי הגלילי, Bein
Rabbi Akiva le-Rabbi Yose HaGlili, whether you demand bones or not, מאי
איכא בינייהו, mai ika beinaihu, אמר רב פפא כויי ונישתיא איכא בינייהו,
amar Rav Pappa kuya ve-nishtayim ika beinaihu,
lips and kidneys. Do mice have lips? Do reptiles have lips? They
do? Okay fine. Alright, so וצריכא, u-tzricha, and you need to say
the debate in both cases, both of about, or you need the
פסוקים pesukim in both places, both by a בהמה and by a
שרץ. sheratz. דאשמעינן בהמה, De-ashmi'inan behema, had you just told me that
there's the טומאה of אבר מן החי by like cows and sheep,
היינו טעמא דלא מטמאי מחיים משום דלא מטמאי בכעדשה, hainu ta'ama de-lo
mitamei mi-chayim mishum de-lo mitamei be-khadasha, then I would have said, but
the reason that there it does not cause טומאה of, excuse me,
let me just check this one second, hold on a minute. Oh
I'm sorry, we're not saying why the פסוק had to tell me
that a limb is מטמא, metamei, why do I have to exclude
the fact that meat alone is not מטמא? metamei. Remember that's the
flip side. A full limb is מטמא, metamei, but meat alone that
comes off is not מטמא. metamei. So you have to say that
in both cases. דאשמעינן בהמה, De-ashmi'inan behema, had you just told me
meat from a בהמה alone is not מטמא, היינו טעמא, hainu ta'ama,
here's the reason, because there's a weakness to the טומאה of a
בהמה, דלא מטמאי מחיים, de-lo mitamei mi-chayim, and here's the reason that
meat taken by life is not מטמא. משום דלא מטמאי בכעדשה, Mishum
de-lo mitamei be-khadasha, it's not, the amount of dead animal you need
to cause טומאה is not the size of a lentil bean, it's
the size of a כזית, kezayit, an olive. So that's stricter than
a שרץ. sheratz. A שרץ sheratz causes טומאה even the size of
a lentil bean, a כעדשה. khadasha. אבל שרץ דמטמא בכעדשה, Aval sheratz
de-mitamei be-khadasha, a שרץ sheratz that causes טומאה even the size of
a lentil bean, אימא דמטמא מחיים, eima de-mitamei mi-chayim, maybe the meat
of a שרץ sheratz even taken from life, even just plain meat,
causes טומאה, בשר מן החי. basar min hachai ואשמעינן שרץ, Ve-ashmi'inan sheratz,
had you just told me there's no בשר מן החי basar min
hachai by a שרץ, sheratz, משום דלא מטמא במשא, mishum de-lo mitamei
be-massa, it doesn't communicate טומאה by being carried, לא מטמא מחיים, lo
mitamei mi-chayim, therefore meat, בשר מן החי basar min hachai. does not
cause טומאה. אבל בהמה דמטמא במשא, Aval behema de-mitamei be-massa, a dead
carcass of an animal that causes טומאה not only through touch but
even through being lifted and carried, so in that way it has
a stronger טומאה, אימא דתטמא מחיים, eima de-titamei mi-chayim, maybe by a
בהמה it will cause טומאה just meat, בשר מן החי. basar min
hachai, וצריכא, u-tzricha, it says both. So I learned both by a
בהמה and by a שרץ sheratz that there's a טומאה of אבר
מן החי, there's a debate what constitutes אבר, but there's a טומאה
of אבר מן החי and there's not a טומאה of בשר מן
החי, and with that we will end for today.